<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The recantacio[n] of Jacke lent late vicare generall to the mooste cruell Antichriste of Rome.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103226</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838983</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838983</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 715:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The recantacio[n] of Jacke lent late vicare generall to the mooste cruell Antichriste of Rome.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Jhon Day and William Seres, dwellyng in Sepulchres parysh, at the signe of the resurrection alitle aboue Holbourne Condiute],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.xlviii [1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>"Jacke Lent" is a not a real person, but rather a fictional narrartor.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3376:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:3376:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iacke Ient late vicare generall to the mooſte cruell Antichriſte of Rome.</p>
            <p>M.D.xlviii.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3376:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:3376:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertain I am (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce) that I am not vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to any one of you, what I am &amp; howe I haue continued my tyme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt you. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I came or whoſe creature I am I thynke fewe of you do as yet know. The moſt part of you, I am ſure, haue hetherto ben perſwaded and in dede I my ſelfe haue confeſſed &amp; taught no leſſe that I came from God, and had my fyrſte beynge of the inſtitution of Chriſt the onely ſonne of the lyuinge God, affirme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge that he, in that he faſted .xl. dayes and fourtie nightes: gaue vs axexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to do the ſame. This is your perſwacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and this haue I heretofore taught, partlye tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe ignoraunce in that I knew
<pb facs="tcp:3376:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
no better, &amp; partly thorowe pride of herte whyche cauſed me to ſeke wayes to be had in price &amp; moone eſtemed amonge you that profeſſe the name of Chriſt. But now that it hath pleaſed the Lorde to open mine eyes and humble mine hert that I maye ſee mine owne eſtate and contente my ſelfe therwyth: I am at this preſente determined to reuoke, retracte and recante, not onely this erroniouſe &amp; falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: but alſo all other ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe doctrine that I haue at anie tyme taught, and wyll out of the ſcriptures declare trulye and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerlye whenſe I came, whoſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature I am, and what abuſes I haue mayntened. Fyrſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalli I acknowledg, that I am no creature of God, nor haue any beynge of hym or hys inſtituci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but am the mere inuencion &amp; ordinaunce of man fyrſt inuented for a polityke ordre euen as other
<pb facs="tcp:3376:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
humayne tradicions haue bene. And accordynge to thys purpoſe of my firſte creation: I am nowe by the maieſtrates of this realme permitted to continewe ſo longe as they ſhal ſe me to be profitable to the publyke and comme weale. And where I haue taught that the example of Chriſt in faſtynge fourtie dayes, &amp; fourtie nyghtes ought to be folowed of you: I vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake it, acknowelegynge that for aſmuche as the faſtynge of Chriſte was a worke aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it was a miracle or thynge to be wondered at and not an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to be folowed more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſte of his miracles and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full workes were. And in verye dede, the way that I haue taught &amp; you haue folowed, is nothinge lyke the example of Chriſte. For he faſted all the tyme of his faſte frome all kindes of ſuſtinaunce, but I haue taught you to faſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:3376:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
fleſhe &amp; white meate onely. Chriſt began hys faſt at the fourth daye of Ianuarie whyche is called the feaſte of the Epiphanie, or the .xii daye, and I haue alwayes defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the tyme to Marche or nigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther abought. Chriſte faſted but once in his lyfe tyme not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge he liued .ii. yeres after. But I haue taught you to faſt euerie yere duringe your life. Thus you ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as it was not poſſible for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aſpire to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſtes wonderfull workes ſo haue you not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a waye anye thynge lyke to hys waye in the foloweynge (as you thought) of hys example. wherfore it is but a fonde perſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of men to thynke that in this (more ſuperſticious the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religious faſt they do any thynge at all folowe the exemple of Chriſt, and I my ſelfe which haue bene a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and ſetter forth of thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine do nowe acknoweledge and
<pb facs="tcp:3376:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
confeſſe myne ignoraunce and ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſticion herein wyllynge al you (my faythfull fryndes, as well fyſhmongers as other) to do the ſame, leſt of your ſtubburnes you cauſe me to be vtterlye baniſhed thys realme, and you loſe all the commodities that you haue by me. Ouer and beſides thys, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knoweledge and confeſſe that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticiouſeli and blindly I haue taught ſome to faſt halfe the time of my raygne, ſome wenſdaye, fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye, and ſaturdaye: and ſome the fridaye from fyſhe. Wyth theſe thynges I haue ſo entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glede the conſciences of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue thought it better to breake all the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God then to omitte one of theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of myne. Theſe thynges I vtterlye reuoke exhorteynge you all my fauourers) to do the ſame, frelye and frankly as I do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrainte or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſion
<pb facs="tcp:3376:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
acknowlegynge and confeſſinge that no humayne tradicions or lawes can bynde the conſciences further then they be founded and buylte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of God. Wherefore I confeſſe &amp; graunte, that all ſuche as be by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powers licenced to eate fleſhe at all tymes maye wyth out grudge of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience do it. More ouer, if neceſſitie ſo require, either thorow pouertie, ſickeneſſe, or otherwiſe: the faithfull maye at all tymes re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue wyth thankes all ſuch ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce as God of hys bountu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe liberalitie geueth them, with out anie licence at al, ſo they do it not in the contempe of anie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ordre nor wyth the offence of theyr weeke brother. Yet all thys not wythſtanding I exhorte you all to faſte and praye, accordynge te the wordes of the prophete, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne you to the Lorde in lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and faſteinge. But here
<pb facs="tcp:3376:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
you muſte be ryght well ware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your prayer be not ſuperſticiouſe numbrynge of ladye pſaltares or other ſette numbres of oriſons (for then they are but lipiaboure) but your prayer muſte be the Lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des prayer, ſpoken euen with the herte, and wyth the holdynge vp of pure ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des wythout bloude, that is, that do not oppreſſe the pore membres of Chriſte, but helpe them. Your faſte alſo muſte be ſuche as Eſay ſpeaketh of in his .lviii. chapiter. You muſte not thynke your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues acceptable vnto God, becauſe you forbeare your meate, becauſe you forſake fleſhe and eate fiſhe: but chiefly and principally in the daye of your faſte you muſte for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare al maner of ſinne, you muſt releaſe your wicked bargaynes, and vſurie contractes, if the pore &amp; nedie be in your daunger more then he is well able to paye: then
<pb facs="tcp:3376:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
muſt you forgyue hym. You muſt alſo refrayne al meates &amp; drinkes that you may feele howe hongre gnaweth the bowelles of the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and then diſtribute to the pore that ſame meate or the price of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame meate that you were accuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med to feede your bodies wyth all. If you ſhall knowe where is an impotent creature, whych lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth neceſſarie clothynge: geue hym of your ſuperfluouſe garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, other elſe ſell them and bye hym garmentes mete for hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the price. If there be any harbour leſſe: leade them into your ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluouſe fermes (wherof you haue to manie) and let them haue dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge there that they may labour the earth and lyue. If you do thys: your light ſhal breake forth euen as the bright morninge ſter and your brightnes ſhalbe as the ſunne at myddaye. But if you do it not: faſte, pray, pippe, ſing, tolle,
<pb facs="tcp:3376:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
ryng, knocke, &amp; knele, tyl you were your kneſe to the bones &amp; all wyll not be worth a louſſe. Manye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperſticiouſe thynges I haue taught, as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuring and ſuperſticious taking of aſhes, and paulme, fyre and the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wherein infantes be baptiſed wyth holye oyle and chriſme. I haue alſo taught the blynde fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of ſaynctes Images, the hangeynge vp, draweynge, and cuttynge downe of the veyle, the waſſhynge of the aultars, Iudas croſſe full of candels, the burie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of the ſacrament, and raye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of the ſame wyth the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge to the croſſe. All theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges I confeſſe to be but vayne &amp; ſuperſticious, &amp; therfore not to be vſed of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men. More o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne I haue ſtoutly defeded anricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion &amp; perticular reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of all ſynnes not forgotten in paine of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the enioyning of penaunce ſatiſfactorie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſam
<pb facs="tcp:3376:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
and that vpon the confidence of theſe penaunce, the ſacramente of the bodye and bloude of Chriſte ſhoulde be worthely receyued, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe not. But nowe I confeſſe that it is onely the humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the herte made vnto God that is accepted of God. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandedynge I wyll that al trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences reſorte vnto a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete and learned counſayloure, to hau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and receiue at hys hande as by an inſtrument, the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table abſolution of the ſpirite, by the hearinge of the greate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die mercies of god towardes the repentante hertes, reherſed vnto them. And where I haue hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made daungerouſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of the ſacrament in both the kyndes, that is in breade and wine as Chriſte inſtituted it: now I thynke it moſte neceſſarie that it be mniſtered and receiued aſwell in the kinde of wine as breade, for
<pb facs="tcp:3376:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
otherwiſe it were not the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of Chriſte, but to inuencion of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thus I make an ende, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting al maner of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie al ſuch vitayllers as haue &amp; do accuſtomably make prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for that kinde of faſteynge that hath bene obſerued in forberinge of one kind of meate and feading of an other: that they wyll nowe prouide for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people mai haue holſome meat to ſuſtein theyr bodies, vpon a reaſonable price. Alſo I exhorte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as heretofore they haue hertelye deſiered of God that a contrarie wind myght kepe backe foren vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle tyll they hadde ſolde theyr ware at wyll: they wyll now pray as hertelye that God of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie wyll proſpere all ſuche as la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the conueighinge of anie kynde of vytayle to any parte of thys realme whereby the pore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons are releaued.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3376:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->By me Iacke lent lately y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter enimy of Chriſt, but nowe (the Lorde be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therfore) conuerted to the Chriſtian fayth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3376:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <p>☞Imprinted at London by Ihon Day, and William Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, dwellyng in Sepulchres paryſh, at the ſigne of the Reſurrection a litle a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue Holbourne Conduite⸫</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>☞Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
